<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Side Projects on Jordan Dworkin</title>
    <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Side Projects on Jordan Dworkin</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jordandworkin.com/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lesion quantification toolkit</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/r-lqt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/r-lqt/</guid>
      <description>Description LQT is an R implementation of the lesion quantification toolkit, based on the paper “Lesion Quantification Toolkit: A MATLAB software tool for estimating grey matter damage and white matter disconnections in patients with focal brain lesions” by Griffis et al. The LQT is a publicly available software package for quantifying the structural impacts of focal brain lesions. It uses atlas-based approaches to estimate parcel-level grey matter lesion loads and multiple measures of white matter disconnection severity that include tract-level disconnection measures, voxel-wise disconnection maps, and parcel-wise disconnection matrices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who do you follow?</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/who-follow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/who-follow/</guid>
      <description>Description Many people in science, tech, and journalism follow mostly white men. While other tools have been created to provide users with gender breakdowns of who they follow on Twitter (e.g., proporti.onl), we wanted to incorporate information on race, as well as the intersection of race and gender. Algorithms are highly flawed in these contexts, so this tool supplements name-based gender/race estimates with self-descriptions drawn directly from Twitter bios. It also gives you the option to improve the initial automatic estimates by manually entering demographic information for a sample of the people you follow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citational justice advocacy and software</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/cite-divers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/cite-divers/</guid>
      <description>Description LQT is an R implementation of the lesion quantification toolkit, based on the paper “Lesion Quantification Toolkit: A MATLAB software tool for estimating grey matter damage and white matter disconnections in patients with focal brain lesions” by Griffis et al. The LQT is a publicly available software package for quantifying the structural impacts of focal brain lesions. It uses atlas-based approaches to estimate parcel-level grey matter lesion loads and multiple measures of white matter disconnection severity that include tract-level disconnection measures, voxel-wise disconnection maps, and parcel-wise disconnection matrices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The landscape of neuroimaging research</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/net-scape/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/net-scape/</guid>
      <description>Description As the field of neuroimaging grows, it can be difficult for scientists within the field to gain and maintain a detailed understanding of its ever-changing landscape. While collaboration and citation networks highlight important contributions within the field, the roles of and relations among specific areas of study can remain quite opaque. Here, I applied techniques from network science to map the landscape of neuroimaging research documented in the journal NeuroImage over the past decade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reskilling to avoid automation</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/job-auto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/job-auto/</guid>
      <description>Description The potential for widespread job automation has become an important topic of discussion in recent years, and it is thought that many American workers may need to learn new skills or transition to new jobs to maintain stable positions in the workforce. Because workers’ existing skills may make such transitions more or less difficult, the likelihood of a given job being automated only tells part of the story. As such, this article exploresthe links between jobs that arise from their necessary skills, knowledge and abilities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment analysis of Stranger Things</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/sthings-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/sthings-art/</guid>
      <description>Description Like a few million other people, I spent the weekend of Oct. 27, 2017, watching Stranger Things season 2, and the following week dealing with minor withdrawal. To help transition back into my PhD research, I decided to teach myself web scraping and sentiment analysis and to apply them to the show&amp;rsquo;s scripts from seasons 1 and 2. The result was a blog post in which I visualize episode-level emotional trajectories, cluster according to common patterns, and analyze episode-to-episode fluctuations in emotional trends.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ranked-choice voting simulation</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/rcv-sim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/rcv-sim/</guid>
      <description>Description Following the 2016 presidential primaries, I attempted to explore the possible outcomes under ranked-choice voting. Using early polls that asked voters for their second-choice candidates, as well as the number of votes cast for each candidate in each primary, I simulated what might have happened in the first 15 Republican primaries and caucuses under an RCV system. Simulations show only modest changes under RCV, with some consolidation against Trump in specific states, but not an overwhelming change in outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
