<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jordan Dworkin</title>
    <link>https://jordandworkin.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jordan Dworkin</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jordandworkin.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Summary metrics of memory subnetwork functional connectivity alterations in multiple sclerosis</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/dni-msj/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/dni-msj/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Memory dysfunction is common in multiple sclerosis (MS); mechanistic understanding of its causes is lacking. Large-scale network resting-state functional connectivity (RSFC) is sensitive to memory dysfunction. Here, we sought to derive and test summary metrics of memory network RSFC. Cognitive data and 3T magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans were collected from 235 MS patients and 35 healthy controls (HCs). Index scores were calculated as RSFC within (anteriority index, AntI) and between (integration index, IntI) dorsomedial anterior temporal and medial temporal memory subnetworks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical methods for diagnosis and screening using neuroimaging data</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/research/neuroimaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/research/neuroimaging/</guid>
      <description>White matter lesions in multiple sclerosis Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a chronic disease of the central nervous system, characterized by progressive cognitive and motor disability. The high financial burden of MS treatments, and their heterogeneity in efficacy across patients, makes the detection of clinical biomarkers a vital goal in MS research. The presence of robust biomarkers could facilitate better individualization of care, allow for more efficient clinical trials, and even provide predictive insight into patients’ likely disease courses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structures of innovation and inequity in scientific research</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/research/metascience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/research/metascience/</guid>
      <description>Citational inequity in scientific research In recent years, science has been pushed to grapple with the vast gender and racial/ethnic imbalances in academic participation. In addition to large and persistent gaps in the proportion of minoritized groups across scientific fields, research has identified imbalances along various measures of academic inclusion and success. Such inequalities have been found in compensation, grant funding, credit for collaborative work, teaching evaluations, hiring and promotions, and authorship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social and environmental determinants of health</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/research/mentalhealth/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/research/mentalhealth/</guid>
      <description>Understanding neurodevelopment and physiological health in children and adolescents Along with a variety of collaborators across Columbia Psychiatry, I help conduct an extensive research program using MRI and biological markers to investigate how children’s environments shape their developmental trajectories. Using prospective cohorts of pregnancy and childrearing as well as large population samples like the Adolescent Brain and Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study, we have ongoing assessments of the role of such diverse exposures as air pollution, maternal SSRI use, cannabis exposure, intergenerational adverse experiences on brain development and physiological functioning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structural brain measures among children with and without ADHD: A cross-sectional US population-based study</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/adhd-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/adhd-brain/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Structural neuroimaging research has identified a variety of abnormalities in cortical and subcortical structures in children with ADHD. However, studies to date have not employed large, non-referred samples, complete with data on potential confounding variables. Here, we tested for differences in structural MRI measures among children with and without ADHD using data from the Adolescent Brain and Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study, the largest paediatric brain imaging study in the USA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citation inequity and gendered citation practices in contemporary physics</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/phys-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/phys-gender/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Similarly to many scientific disciplines, neuroscience has increasingly attempted to confront pervasive gender imbalances. Although publishing and conference participation are often highlighted, recent research has called attention to the prevalence of gender imbalance in citations. Because of the downstream effects of citations on visibility and career advancement, understanding the role of gender in citation practices is vital for addressing scientific inequity. Here, we investigate whether gendered patterns are present in neuroscience citations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noise complaint patterns in New York City: Socioeconomic disparities and COVID-19 exacerbations</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/noise-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/noise-covid/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Excessive environmental noise exposure and noise annoyance have been linked to adverse physical and mental health outcomes. Although socioeconomic disparities in acoustically measured and geospatially estimated noise have been established, less is known about disparities in noise complaints, one of the most common sources of distress reported to local municipalities. Furthermore, although some studies have posited urban quieting during the COVID-19 pandemic, little empirical work has probed this and probed noise complaints during the pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Association of regional white matter hyperintensities with longitudinal Alzheimer-like pattern of neurodegeneration in older adults</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/alz-wmh/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/alz-wmh/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Small vessel cerebrovascular disease, visualized as white matter hyperintensities (WMH), is associated with cognitive decline and risk of clinical Alzheimer disease (AD). One way in which small vessel cerebrovascular disease could contribute to AD is through the promotion of neurodegeneration; the effect of small vessel cerebrovascular disease on neurodegeneration may differ across racial and ethnic groups. To examine whether WMH volume is associated with cortical thinning over time and subsequent memory functioning and whether the association between WMH volume and cortical thinning differs among racial and ethnic groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Timing-specific associations between income-to-needs ratio and hippocampal and amygdala volumes in middle childhood</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/brain-inr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/brain-inr/</guid>
      <description>Abstract It is well known that financial disadvantage is associated with alterations in brain development in regions critical to socioemotional well-being such as the hippocampus and the amygdala. Yet little is known about whether family income at different points in development is differentially associated with these structures. Furthermore, little is known about which environmental factors statistically mediate associations between income and subcortical structure. Using a longitudinal birth cohort and linear mixed-effects models, we identified associations between income-to-needs ratio (INR) at 6 timepoints throughout childhood and hippocampal and amygdala volumes at age 7–9 years (n = 41; 236 INR measurements; 41 brain measurements).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lesion quantification toolkit</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/r-lqt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/r-lqt/</guid>
      <description>Description LQT is an R implementation of the lesion quantification toolkit, based on the paper “Lesion Quantification Toolkit: A MATLAB software tool for estimating grey matter damage and white matter disconnections in patients with focal brain lesions” by Griffis et al. The LQT is a publicly available software package for quantifying the structural impacts of focal brain lesions. It uses atlas-based approaches to estimate parcel-level grey matter lesion loads and multiple measures of white matter disconnection severity that include tract-level disconnection measures, voxel-wise disconnection maps, and parcel-wise disconnection matrices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the mental health of transgender and gender nonbinary individuals</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/lgbt-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/lgbt-covid/</guid>
      <description>Abstract While the COVID-19 pandemic in the United States disproportionately impacts marginalized communities, no empiric US-based research has focused specifically on transgender and gender nonbinary (TGNB) people. We examined the pandemic’s impact on an established longitudinal cohort of TGNB individuals (N = 208) by administering an online survey between March-June 2020. We used multivariable linear regression to examine reduced LGBTQ/TGNB community support and disruptions in gender-affirming health care as predictors of psychological distress during the pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Racial and ethnic imbalance in neuroscience reference lists and intersections with gender</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/neuro-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/neuro-race/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Discrimination against racial and ethnic minority groups exists in the academy, and the associated biases impact hiring and promotion, publication rates, grant funding, and awards. Precisely how racial and ethnic bias impacts the manner in which the scientific community engages with the ideas of academics in minority groups has yet to be fully elucidated. Citations are a marker of such community engagement, as well as a currency used to attain career milestones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who do you follow?</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/who-follow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/who-follow/</guid>
      <description>Description Many people in science, tech, and journalism follow mostly white men. While other tools have been created to provide users with gender breakdowns of who they follow on Twitter (e.g., proporti.onl), we wanted to incorporate information on race, as well as the intersection of race and gender. Algorithms are highly flawed in these contexts, so this tool supplements name-based gender/race estimates with self-descriptions drawn directly from Twitter bios. It also gives you the option to improve the initial automatic estimates by manually entering demographic information for a sample of the people you follow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The extent and drivers of gender imbalance in neuroscience reference lists</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/neuro-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/neuro-gender/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Similarly to many scientific disciplines, neuroscience has increasingly attempted to confront pervasive gender imbalances. Although publishing and conference participation are often highlighted, recent research has called attention to the prevalence of gender imbalance in citations. Because of the downstream effects of citations on visibility and career advancement, understanding the role of gender in citation practices is vital for addressing scientific inequity. Here, we investigate whether gendered patterns are present in neuroscience citations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citational justice advocacy and software</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/cite-divers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/cite-divers/</guid>
      <description>Description LQT is an R implementation of the lesion quantification toolkit, based on the paper “Lesion Quantification Toolkit: A MATLAB software tool for estimating grey matter damage and white matter disconnections in patients with focal brain lesions” by Griffis et al. The LQT is a publicly available software package for quantifying the structural impacts of focal brain lesions. It uses atlas-based approaches to estimate parcel-level grey matter lesion loads and multiple measures of white matter disconnection severity that include tract-level disconnection measures, voxel-wise disconnection maps, and parcel-wise disconnection matrices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A local group differences test for subject-level multivariate density neuroimaging outcomes</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/density-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/density-test/</guid>
      <description>Abstract A great deal of neuroimaging research focuses on voxel-wise analysis or segmentation of damaged tissue, yet many diseases are characterized by diffuse or non-regional neuropathology. In simple cases, these processes can be quantified using summary statistics of voxel intensities. However, the manifestation of a disease process in imaging data is often unknown, or appears as a complex and nonlinear relationship between the voxel intensities on various modalities. When the relevant pattern is unknown, summary statistics are often unable to capture differences between disease groups, and their use may encourage post hoc searches for the optimal summary measure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network-driven differences in mobility and optimal transitions among automatable jobs</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/job-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/job-network/</guid>
      <description>Abstract The potential for widespread job automation has become an important topic of discussion in recent years, and it is thought that many American workers may need to learn new skills or transition to new jobs to maintain stable positions in the workforce. Because workers’ existing skills may make such transitions more or less difficult, the likelihood of a given job being automated only tells part of the story. As such, this study uses network science and statistics to investigate the links between jobs that arise from their necessary skills, knowledge and abilities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The emergent integrated network structure of scientific research</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/pnas-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/pnas-net/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Scientific research is often thought of as being conducted by individuals and small teams striving for disciplinary advances. Yet as a whole, this endeavor more closely resembles a complex and integrated system of people, papers, and ideas. Studies of co-authorship and citation networks have revealed important structural properties of researchers and articles, but currently the structure of scientific ideas themselves is not well understood. In this study, we posit that topic networks may be a useful framework for revealing the nature of conceptual relationships.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 13:38:41 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>** Contact page don&amp;rsquo;t contain a body, just the front matter above. See form.html in the layouts folder.
Formspree requires a (free) account and new form to be set up. The link is made on the final published url in the field: Restrict to Domain. It is possible to register up to 2 emails free and you can select which one you want the forms to go to within Formspree in the Settings tab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capturing naturally occurring emotional suppression as it unfolds in couple interactions</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/emo-sup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/emo-sup/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Most research examining the consequences of suppressing emotional expression has focused on either experimentally manipulated and conscious suppression, or self-reported suppression behavior. This study examined suppression as it naturally occurred in couple (n = 105) discussions regarding a challenging topic. A Suppression Index (SI) was created by calculating the difference between continuous self-reports of emotional experience, obtained using cued video recall, and coders’ continuous ratings of expressed emotion. Suppression was common for both men and women, though there was also substantial individual variation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automated integration of multimodal MRI for the probabilistic detection of the central vein sign in MS lesions</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/ajnr-cvs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/ajnr-cvs/</guid>
      <description>Abstract The central vein sign is a promising MR imaging diagnostic biomarker for multiple sclerosis. Recent studies have demonstrated that patients with MS have higher proportions of white matter lesions with the central vein sign compared with those with diseases that mimic MS on MR imaging. However, the clinical application of the central vein sign as a biomarker is limited by interrater differences in the adjudication of the central vein sign as well as the time burden required for the determination of the central vein sign for each lesion in a patient&amp;rsquo;s full MR imaging scan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The landscape of neuroimaging research</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/net-scape/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/net-scape/</guid>
      <description>Description As the field of neuroimaging grows, it can be difficult for scientists within the field to gain and maintain a detailed understanding of its ever-changing landscape. While collaboration and citation networks highlight important contributions within the field, the roles of and relations among specific areas of study can remain quite opaque. Here, I applied techniques from network science to map the landscape of neuroimaging research documented in the journal NeuroImage over the past decade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The landscape of neuroimaging research</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/nim-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/nim-net/</guid>
      <description>Abstract As the field of neuroimaging grows, it can be difficult for scientists within the field to gain and maintain a detailed understanding of its ever-changing landscape. While collaboration and citation networks highlight important contributions within the field, the roles of and relations among specific areas of study can remain quite opaque. Here, we apply techniques from network science to map the landscape of neuroimaging research documented in the journal NeuroImage over the past decade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reskilling to avoid automation</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/job-auto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/job-auto/</guid>
      <description>Description The potential for widespread job automation has become an important topic of discussion in recent years, and it is thought that many American workers may need to learn new skills or transition to new jobs to maintain stable positions in the workforce. Because workers’ existing skills may make such transitions more or less difficult, the likelihood of a given job being automated only tells part of the story. As such, this article exploresthe links between jobs that arise from their necessary skills, knowledge and abilities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An automated statistical technique for counting distinct multiple sclerosis lesions</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/ajnr-count/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/ajnr-count/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Lesion load is a common biomarker in multiple sclerosis, yet it has historically shown modest association with clinical outcome. Lesion count, which encapsulates the natural history of lesion formation and is thought to provide complementary information, is difficult to assess in patients with confluent (ie, spatially overlapping) lesions. We introduce a statistical technique for cross-sectionally counting pathologically distinct lesions. MR imaging was used to assess the probability of a lesion at each location.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian nonparametric generative models for causal inference with missing at random covariates</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/bnp-caus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/bnp-caus/</guid>
      <description>Abstract We propose a general Bayesian nonparametric (BNP) approach to causal inference in the point treatment setting. The joint distribution of the observed data (outcome, treatment, and confounders) is modeled using an enriched Dirichlet process. The combination of the observed data model and causal assumptions allows us to identify any type of causal effect—differences, ratios, or quantile effects, either marginally or for subpopulations of interest. The proposed BNP model is well-suited for causal inference problems, as it does not require parametric assumptions about the distribution of confounders and naturally leads to a computationally efficient Gibbs sampling algorithm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment analysis of Stranger Things</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/sthings-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/sthings-art/</guid>
      <description>Description Like a few million other people, I spent the weekend of Oct. 27, 2017, watching Stranger Things season 2, and the following week dealing with minor withdrawal. To help transition back into my PhD research, I decided to teach myself web scraping and sentiment analysis and to apply them to the show&amp;rsquo;s scripts from seasons 1 and 2. The result was a blog post in which I visualize episode-level emotional trajectories, cluster according to common patterns, and analyze episode-to-episode fluctuations in emotional trends.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting recovery though estimation and visualization of active and incident lesions</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/les-pred/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/publications/les-pred/</guid>
      <description>Abstract The goal of this study was to develop a model that integrates imaging and clinical information observed at lesion incidence for predicting the recovery of white matter lesions in multiple sclerosis (MS) patients. Demographic, clinical, and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) data were obtained from 60 subjects with MS as part of a natural history study at the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke. A total of 401 lesions met the inclusion criteria and were used in the study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ranked-choice voting simulation</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/rcv-sim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/projects/rcv-sim/</guid>
      <description>Description Following the 2016 presidential primaries, I attempted to explore the possible outcomes under ranked-choice voting. Using early polls that asked voters for their second-choice candidates, as well as the number of votes cast for each candidate in each primary, I simulated what might have happened in the first 15 Republican primaries and caucuses under an RCV system. Simulations show only modest changes under RCV, with some consolidation against Trump in specific states, but not an overwhelming change in outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contributors</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/contributors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/contributors/</guid>
      <description>Thank you to all the folks who contributed to this Hugo template: Desirée De Leon 🦒, Garrick Aden-Buie 🧙‍♀️, Allison Horst 🐕, Maëlle Salmon 🎣, Christophe Dervieux 🖍, Yihui Xie 🥋, Athanasia Monika Mowinckel 💜, Jannik Buhr 🦦, and Eric Anderson and the team at Formspree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>License</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/license/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/license/</guid>
      <description>My blog posts are released under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
