<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>My Academic Research on Jordan Dworkin</title>
    <link>https://jordandworkin.com/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in My Academic Research on Jordan Dworkin</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jordandworkin.com/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Statistical methods for diagnosis and screening using neuroimaging data</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/research/neuroimaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/research/neuroimaging/</guid>
      <description>White matter lesions in multiple sclerosis Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a chronic disease of the central nervous system, characterized by progressive cognitive and motor disability. The high financial burden of MS treatments, and their heterogeneity in efficacy across patients, makes the detection of clinical biomarkers a vital goal in MS research. The presence of robust biomarkers could facilitate better individualization of care, allow for more efficient clinical trials, and even provide predictive insight into patients’ likely disease courses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structures of innovation and inequity in scientific research</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/research/metascience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/research/metascience/</guid>
      <description>Citational inequity in scientific research In recent years, science has been pushed to grapple with the vast gender and racial/ethnic imbalances in academic participation. In addition to large and persistent gaps in the proportion of minoritized groups across scientific fields, research has identified imbalances along various measures of academic inclusion and success. Such inequalities have been found in compensation, grant funding, credit for collaborative work, teaching evaluations, hiring and promotions, and authorship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social and environmental determinants of health</title>
      <link>https://jordandworkin.com/research/mentalhealth/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jordandworkin.com/research/mentalhealth/</guid>
      <description>Understanding neurodevelopment and physiological health in children and adolescents Along with a variety of collaborators across Columbia Psychiatry, I help conduct an extensive research program using MRI and biological markers to investigate how children’s environments shape their developmental trajectories. Using prospective cohorts of pregnancy and childrearing as well as large population samples like the Adolescent Brain and Cognitive Development (ABCD) Study, we have ongoing assessments of the role of such diverse exposures as air pollution, maternal SSRI use, cannabis exposure, intergenerational adverse experiences on brain development and physiological functioning.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
